so I'm very happy to introduce uh John
solitario from rocket uh he's a senior
product manager there and before joining
rocket he was at Salesforce and uh he's
also a Stanford
man so without further Ado I'm going to
hand over to John fre talk all Vector
search is hybrid
search
awesome and and thank you for the intro
hey everyone I'm John solitario I'm a
product lead at Rocket and today we're
going to start off with a pretty bold
claim and that claim is that all Vector
search is actually hybrid search and I
know this is definitely going to invite
some controvers so I'm going to skip
right to the
end and by starting
and skipping to the end I need to start
with the title all Vector search is
hybrid search what this really means is
that all Vector search applications are
actually hybrid search
applications now I don't always mean
this quite literally and this is very
strongly worded as this is a talk at a
conference but the argument that I'm
going to lay out is that the majority of
product experiences are greatly improved
when you start to think about
hybridizing your search when you take
that pure Vector search which can mean a
lot of things and then adding or
augmenting creating guard rails around
that to really increase
relevance and increase the quality of
your
results
now bear with me as we go through this
but let's all in this room you know
assume that this is the case and with
that we can actually make some really
interesting conclusions and we can
actually expand how we start to think
about this
problem and so stemming from the first
statement let's assume that all is true
that's something we believe in then we
can get to our next statement here that
all Vector search infrastructure is
therefore actually hybrid search
infrastructure so if agree with the
first this naturally flows in to the
second but now here's the interesting
thing that really ties these two
together is that hybrid search and
hybrid search infrastructure is actually
a completely new kind of thing and it's
not completely new because it actually
borrows from three distinct and
seemingly related fields we can talk
about Vector search we can talk about
search and we can also talk about
database databases and all the
infrastructure involved in these
different
paradigms and and I know here today this
is a search conference this is a search
audience but there's a lot that we can
learn from other fields and we can also
by you know learning from those fields
looking at those fields can start to see
how they intersect and as they intersect
we can really learn a lot from lessons
that we actually learn perhaps in a very
hard way in some of these other spaces
and in some of these other
groups and so with that let's get into
so I'm not going to spend too much time
on this I know we have a huge range of
experience backgrounds in the room just
want to really do a
quick walk through a vector search to
make sure we all understand what this is
what it means why it's important I'll
then quickly run through what hybrid
search means really creating a
definition around that and then once
we're all aligned and on the same page
about these terms we can start to think
about how they come together and how
Vector search becomes hybrid search so
what is Vector search vector search
enables us to take these
unstructured problems unstructured data
unstructured statements and turn those
into something that is more easily
quantifiable and more easily measurable
we have some ambiguous questions show me
things I might like show me images of
cats we turn those into embeddings and
then based off those embeddings we're
able to search across any type of store
that is storing those embeddings and we
can find ones that are similar so
instead of having this unstructured
problem we go from give me an embedding
let me find the closest or most similar
embeddings and when we think about how
to actually do this and how to structure
that search we can always start with our
exact nearest neighbors algorithm this
is Brute Force this is given that
embedding search across all my
embeddings and return the ones that are
the most similar this works great when
you have smaller data sets but it very
quickly becomes expensive as we expand
to larger numbers of embeddings and also
as we increase the size of those
embeddings and so to solve this problem
we then can start talking about our
approximate nearest neighbor search Now
using clever algorithms clever indexing
techniques we can trade off some of our
recall or accuracy of those results with
efficiency and with that efficiency
we're actually able to search across
these embeddings much more
quickly and
therefore reduce the overhead
that is required gred we are perhaps
trading off some accuracy and the
quality of those
results but the moment we start talking
about approximate things this becomes a
new source of pain right when we think
about the traditional database World
everything's explicit everything's exact
but in the search World you all have
actually been thinking about this
problem for quite a long time I know
many of you in this audience are
probably very familiar with something
like one that's an approximate algorithm
that really benefits Us in Tech search
use
cases so that's Vector search and now
want to lay out hybrid search now I'll
spend a little bit more time on hybrid
search because this is a very popular
and overload loaded term at the
moment and it's become very popular in
this world of AI and Vector
search but I actually want us to take a
much broader definition what hybrid
search
is and as we think about this we can
actually think about just combining two
or more
indexes and asking those indexes to
increase relevance but also potentially
to increase performance and
efficiency but today we're really
restricted or have been restricted to
talking about hybrid search as Vector
search plus something
else so this true hybrid search as we
can call it is more or less usually
searching across two different embedding
types we have our DSE embedding on one
end and something that may be generated
by an llm or another embedding model and
then we have our sparse embeddings on
the other
side but these sparse embeddings are
really just a
representation of keyword
boosting we create these
embeddings and we can think about you
Associated algorithms like bm25
PF
IDF and so now we have two different
search paradigms we have across the
spars and Bings we have across the nens
and betting and then we need to think
about combining those results in some
way now we can use something like
reciprocal rank Fusion or something even
more simple like a weighted average of
scores but this and today has really
been the main topic of discussion around
hybrid
search but what about search with met
filtering this is another very popular
term in the vector search world and it's
treated as a distinctly separate
problem here's a quick example show me
the most relevant documents but those
that have been let's say updated or
created within the past 30
days and if this document meets my
criteria I can think about really
boosting this score right say plus a
thousand to that similarity or to that
relevance and then if it doesn't match I
can think about greatly waiting that
score in a negative way minus 1000 or
even some cases minus infinity right
this isn't something that we would want
to show and display in our
results but at the end of the day this
is still hybrid search right we're just
taking much more extreme weights to that
search paradig and that search approach
and to ultimately influence the output
of our
results now what about two-stage
retrieval and
reranking this is a completely different
problem
right with this approach we use in many
cases a very inexpensive
index to find let's say our initial list
of candidates this case we could say
it's 100 candidates and then we may use
a much more expensive index or algorithm
or model
who then rank those 100 candidates and
let's say return the top 10 now this is
uniquely different because in this case
we're actually combining two indexes and
using the first to maximize the
computational resources of the
second but again we're back to the
situation where we're searching and
using multiple paradigms potentially
multiple
indexes and so hybrid search actually
means much more than just you know dense
search plus a sparse search we can think
about metadata filtering within the lens
of hybrid search and we could also even
think about two-stage retrieval within
the lens of hybrid search and this is by
no means an exhaustive list right let's
think back to that more broad definition
whenever we're thinking about leveraging
two or more indexes to generate
results we can talk about and think
about hybrid search and then we can also
combine and mix and match these
different strategies different
algorithms these in different indexes in
a variety of
ways and so this is how we're kind of
leveling up this conversation around
what hybrid search means and what it is
and how it's going to impact our
applications and ultimately our search
experiences and so now I'm going to get
into the exciting part of this talk
where we're going to walk through how
Vector search becomes hybrid search or
why it becomes or how it becomes and
what this really
means and and so let's first lay out
what's the dream of vector search right
I can take a model I can embed my
query and after I embed that query into
this search space of results I can then
pull the most similar items documents
whatever that may
be and relying on this power of AI we
can
turn our nearest neighbor or to our
nearest neighbor algorithms to really
answer and resolve all of our problems
around search recommendation and
Q&A now the slides as you can see
probably meant to inspire some
doubt and we have one big problem with
this approach is that arguably these
models are insufficiently
Advanced now one day perhaps in the near
future perhaps in the much further
future this could change change right
we've seen huge advancements in
foundational models over the past couple
of
years and with that this could actually
change how we think about the problem
but right now when we generate these
embeddings we run our Vector searches
they're amazing at finding semantic
likeness or semantic similarity but
they're terrible at respecting Pacific
guard
rails now
I'm going to walk through a couple
examples to really highlight the
argument I've laid out here and laid out
at the beginning of this talk that any
product
experience primarily powered by Vector
surge is only going to be made better by
adding filtering rules and perhaps even
Other Bar
rails and this perspective has really
been developed from
working with a huge range of customers
over the past two years and so I want to
walk through some of their examples and
how moving from Vector search to hybrid
search has really increased the quality
of their products and the quality of
those
experiences and so the first example
that I'm going to start with is all
around in app
search and in this situation we can
think about kind of a standard SAS
application in this case may be looking
for specific objects let's say specific
accounts and as I'm prompting from that
search there may be very explicit things
that I'm calling out and that I'm
directing right perhaps I'm looking for
all accounts where some of the employees
may have worked for Geico in the
past perhaps I want to limit my search
to a certain geography right I want to
look for the phrase Virginia in my
address perhaps I'm actually only
interested in specific sectors of the
economy or of companies let's say I'm
actually just looking for companies or
accounts related to people selling auto
insurance and also maybe I want to look
at instances where our sales team is
actively
engaged with the account with the people
associated with the
account in all these cases we can really
think about how we're augmenting this
initial more fuzzy problem of show me
relevant
accounts I really want to augment that
with very specific data and in this
situation it's text Data you think about
text matching fuzzy text matching and a
variety of other
strategies so that's an AB
search now I'm going to talk about
recommendations and so on the screen I
have a screenshot of this product called
whatnot whatnot is a live auction site
they have live streams where people are
auctioning off
goods and whenever users enter my
application I want to recommend to them
a variety of live
streams now these live streams are very
ephemeral right they may only last on
the order of magnitude of minutes and so
perhaps I want to make sure that I'm
recommending streams that have recently
started I don't want to show them an
auction that that it's end and perhaps
they're not even auctioning off any
items or objects at that moment in
time perhaps I also want to show live
streams that have a lot of Engagement
they have a lot of people uh involved in
the auction right this is a much more
exciting atmosphere to join in as
opposed to an auction where you may only
have a handful of people so maybe I want
to filter
for live streams that have more than a
certain number of viewers perhaps I'm
actively looking for very specific items
things that I want to you know bid an
auction on this case let's say I'm
actually only interested in sports
memorabilia I really want to restrict
the recommendations to this explicit
category and then perhaps I have other
functionality built in my application
let's say I can follow given sellers on
my application or on the app and with
that I want to recommend the sellers
that have live auctions going or live
streams going that have followed in the
past and so these are all examples of
how we're thinking about augmenting or
restricting those recommendations in a
variety of
ways and finally I want to talk about
retrieval augmented
generation rag I know there's a lot of
talks here that are focused on Rag and
rag Frameworks and strategies but for
this we just want to focus on the
example and so in this situation
I'm a major airline and I've built an
application to help my flight attendant
or perhaps anyone working at the
airline I want to give them access to
this
huge collection of documents protocols
procedures that should dictate how
people can handle certain
situations in this case whenever a plane
is landing into a specific airport
there's actually very specific
procedures involved with that process so
let's say I'm flying from New York
SFO I have a question about you know the
initial let's say kind of pre-landing
procedures and so I actually want to
restrict that to the procedures involved
with SFO or perhaps another airport in
the Bay
Area it's directly tied to the phrases
that we might want to look
for and as we know in most you know
Enterprises there's so many different
documents that can exist that have been
created years ago that may be relevant
may be irrelevant but I want to make
sure that I'm only showing documents
that have been updated recently because
those are the ones I can have the most
trust in and then finally what about
permissions right we have a very
specific person accessing this
application we're thinking about this is
being built across you know the entire
company we really need to respect we
need to honor and we need to follow the
permissions that are laid out by that
organization and in this case I only
want to surface documents that are
actually meant to access or to have
access by this given role
and so with this I hope you all can
start to see this value that we have
around adding these guard rails
augmenting the experience to create more
relevant
results and create a more relevant
product and so as we made this jump as
we've got on this journey from Vector
search to hybrid search we now have this
very interesting new problem is that
we're not only talking about Vector
search infrastructure anymore we're
actually talking about hybrid search
infrastructure and this problem kind of
really
highlights a multiple indexing problem
instead of one single index is very
clever very powerful we have to think
how we're searching across multiple and
other indexes
we need to think about the cooperation
across these how we leverage them how we
take advantage of them
together and this is when our Vector
search
infrastructure actually starts to look a
lot more like search infrastructure and
also database infrastructure as
well and we know that both of these
groups of Technology have actually been
optimizing this problem for quite a long
time when we think about any type of
query needs to access and hit on
multiple indexes so we can actually
start to think about how all the
advancements in both of these fields all
the great ideas actually apply to this
new problem of hybrid
search but there's a caveat here and
that caveat is that Ann indexes our
approximate nearest neighbor algorithm
indexes are especially difficult to
integrate and so we're going to walk
through why that may
be I'm going to start with a motivating
example
so we're going to start with
recommendations right show me the
recommendations but you want those
recommendations to respect or to follow
certain guard rails or
criteria perhaps I'm searching for
products within an application right I
want to
respect any filters any information that
the user inputs perhaps I'm only looking
for white t-shirts or white shoes and
perhaps you know I want to stick to a
certain budget
we can also think about something like
inventory right we only want to
recommend concerts that have tickets
available or perhaps even friend
recommendation right we want to
recommend friends that are actively
offline when we recommend them you can
then start a
conversation
and each of these groups of criteria or
groups of problems are actually really
well solved by completely separate
Technologies in some way completely
separate indexes we have this fuzzy
problem have shown me
recommendations which as we can see as
we all know can be greatly resolved and
helped by something like our Vector
index but then we also have this very
explicit
criteria right a criteria is categorical
or it's arrange looks a lot like a
series of predicates and with that we
know this can be very well solved by a
relational index and so we have two
indexes here that we really need to
leverage and think about using to
ultimately solve our
problem and so this gets to twoo
great and obvious but not great
approaches and we're going to start with
the first one here on the left which is
pre
filtering with the pre-filtering
approach we're actually going to filter
out all our vectors that don't meet our
metadata filter right so we're only
going to pull those that meet our
criteria and then with this new set of
results with this new list of candidates
we're going to exhaustively scan those
we're going to per our exhaustive K&N
search and we're going to find the
results that are the most
similar and so this is our pre-filtering
approach and as you can see this Maps
one on the first side to a very kind of
simple straightforward classic
relational database query and then on
the second component here
Arcane and search as we talked about
earlier now there's another way to do
this and that's with a postfiltering
approach and this is when we apply the
filter after we perform that Vector
search and so we first we have this huge
bin collection of documents and we want
to pull out all the similar in vectors
using that Vector
in and then we want to filter out
candidates that don't match our criteria
this looks
great until we have a little bit of a
problem perhaps all the embeddings that
I had initially extracted the ones that
are most relevant based off of our
embedding space don't actually meet our
filtering
criteria and so with that I may actually
have to go back to step one I actually
may need to return more candidates or a
different part of our embedding space to
then ultimately get to step
two and what really matters here is the
selectivity of our filters the
selectivity of the things and the
candidates that we're ultimately looking
for and so with these two obvious but
not cretive approaches we can see that
pre-filtering works extremely well when
I have very selective filters when these
filters are very selective I only in
Return of very small subset of the
documents from my larger collection or
set and then I don't need to worry about
that computational overhead of
Performing my KNN or my exact search but
we can really see how this falls apart
if I have very non-selective filters if
my filters are non- selective I'm then
returning perhaps almost all the
documents in that collection and then
this exhaustive search becomes extremely
expensive and also may become much more
slower then we have our post filtering
approach right this works great when the
filters are non- selective as you can
see in the previous example we never get
to that third step we never have to go
back kind of reconsider and repol all of
our
candidates but when filters are really
selective you can see us getting in a
loop of having to extract documents
apply the filters they don't meet these
you know criteria and then we have to go
back to stage one and that can go on
indefinitely eventually in some cases it
actually leads to an entirely you know
exhaustive scan of your collection and
of your data
set and so now I'm going to switch to a
completely different
problem and with this problem I want you
all to imagine a
database that database has two indexes
we have our row store on one end is kind
of your standard relational
index and then we have an inverted index
on the other
side and this inverted index provides us
a lookup to that rose store or to that
relational index and so in this case I
have a mapping from all documents where
the name of the user is John to you know
the documents that meet that criteria
and so you can think about this on kind
of a field categorical and then also
document
basis and this ultimately leads to one
of the fundamental ideas around indexes
right one of the fundamental challenges
but also one of the fundamental
advantages is that as we're accessing
and extracting these documents we can
think about accessing that row store
scanning that row score it's actually
much faster on a per row access
basis but when we have something like an
inverted Index this enables us to look
at a far fewer number of
rows but we can start to see a Tipping
Point here between these two access
patterns and between these two
indexes and so to highlight this I'm
going to walk through a quick example we
have two queries that on the surface
look really
similar and the first query we're
filtering for users or they may have the
name
John and in the second we're filtering
for users where their status is active
and you think about this also perhaps
the be inactive and perhaps we use you
know a variety of different names
here and although these queries look
very similar they're actually very
different in the first case we may only
have one user with the name John
probably not going to be the case but we
can imagine there's probably you know a
smaller subset of users with that
name but then perhaps the status whether
it's active or inactive May apply to the
majority of our users for the majority
of rows in the data
set and this creates a new problem and a
new tradeoff this implies The Tipping
Point that we're ENC
capturing and that Tipping Point is
directly tied to the indexes that we
want to use or access in the first case
it's going to be much more
efficient much more performant for me to
use my inverted index I can look up the
documents where the name is John and
then automatically extract those
documents from my roast store and
therefore have to pull and scan a much
smaller amount of documents and a much
smaller amount of
pages now in the second case where
almost all my documents submit this
criteria I don't need my inverted Index
this is you know something that I can
really look across my entire data set
and extract the majority of these that
meet this
criteria and so what does this
mean problems starting to look somewhat
familiar it really goes back to the
selectivity of these
filters in one case we have a filter
that's extremely
selective and in another case where the
filter is non- selective and based off
of this selectivity we actually want to
adopt different strategies for
extracting
information and extracting documents
and so what does this
mean in the database world right deep
down in our system we have something
called a query
Optimizer and that query Optimizer has
two different ways of doing something
two different ways of executing these
queries two different ways two different
options for really selecting which index
to
use and the right way to do this is
completely based off of the selectivity
of these
filters and again this is all sounding
very familiar for multiple
reasons the first one that I want to
highlight here is a fairly famous paper
that was published in
1979 this paper is all about access path
selection within
databases and it's all about estimating
the selectivity of filters or filtering
criteria predicates to determine which
index to use and this paper highlights a
lot of clever ways a lot of Statistics
that we can use on our data to actually
determine that most efficient
approach and how to weigh the cost of
these two different search patterns or
search paradigms
and with these you know selectivity
estimates for quer
optimization this
concept you know well written about in
1979 is over 40 years
old seems like a long time ago what this
means is that we've also made 40 years
of progress on how to handle this type
of problem how to measure it where to
apply it so on and so forth
and a lot of this is extremely relevant
to things that we've been talking about
for really just within the past two
years right when we first really started
pulling apart Factor search we started
talking about metata filtering was
really back in
1979 and so want to have a a call to
action here everyone in the audience
that we should actually really go back
and reread and revisit all of the
advances and all the research in both
the database and search spaces and think
about how we're actually applying that
to this new breed and new realm of
indexes which are our a&n indexes are
approximate nearest neighbor
indexes and with this new lens we may
actually rise a much different
conclusions but it also gives us an
opportunity to really learn from these
fields that have dealing with very
similar problem for a very long period
of
time and so what does this all me
at the end of the
day I think one we're actually starting
to see vectors Vector search Vector andj
go
mainstream and as they go mainstream we
actually joining a much larger body of
research in an area that's been
researched for a very long period of
time and you know we also have a ton of
work to do here and I think all of us
have seen the rapid development over the
past several years but I think and can
only expect more development in a lot of
these ways and ultimately an eventual
merging of these different
infrastructures again these things have
been very distinct in the past when we
think about Vector surch think about
search we think about
databases but they're actually starting
to look more and more similar and we can
start to see these different
Technologies these different paradigms
these different communities all coming
together and learning from each
other and so with that I'll conclude
that all Vector search is hybrid search
hope I've convinced you all of this or
at least it's a problem we should start
thinking about and just want to give a
huge thank you to the
audience and also a shout out to Julie
Mills and LS Brandy who helped me pull
together this
presentation thank you John so do we
have any questions for
John straight up the goes up the front
got hi so um you were talking about like
in place verus um I mean I mean um
preing and post fing have into quadrant
like in place
filtering like what's your opinion on
that yeah so there's a lot of people
that talk about this you know single
stage metadata filtering where this
approach perhaps removes some of the
pitfalls of your pre-filtering approach
or your post filtering approach and it's
actually pretty easy to see how that may
work with something like an inverted
index structure
right in some ways I have these posting
lists of embeddings that are similar the
one that I'm searching across and then
I'm intersecting those with other
posting lists that fit some criteria or
some filter now the challenge here is
that that approach only May apply to
let's say an inverted type of you know
file index structure which is something
like face um I believe quadrant uses
something like hsw to actually do their
Vector search but then you can think
about you know there's 810 plus
different type of you know popular
similarity search Vector search
algorithms and so there's actually a lot
of ways to think about solving this
problem quadrant I'm sure has unique
Solutions I haven't tested it myself so
I can't comment on how that works and if
there are edge cases if there are
situations where that becomes a
challenge but we're already starting to
think about really clever ways to
combine these two and so I think that's
a great example of how you know one you
know very popular Vector database is
approaching
that okay and just just to remind people
watching us on Zoom please do submit
questions through the zoom chat and
we'll ask them on your behalf we have
another question from the
room hi yeah you talked a lot about uh
filters but especially for rag apps um
how do you uh do you have any
recommendations on how you would go
about extracting filters from user
queries themselves without having to
specify it
manually yes that's a a great question
and I think that probably expands much
further Beyond you know how we're
thinking about searching across
documents and actually applying those
filters there's a lot of research that's
been done over the past five to 10 years
we have like entity
extraction um different approaches
especially in the machine Learning
Community actually look at a blob of
text and let's say PL out things that
are like pronouns or things that have
you know very specific meaning or are
very specifically related to the content
and so I think that is probably more in
the machine learning community in terms
of actually extracting what those
filters could be but a lot of these
filters you you know may extend beyond
what is actually in the user text right
so one of the examples that we use May
is perhaps you only want to reference
documents that have an updated or
created in the past 30 days that can
apply to almost all the queries that you
may run if we think about we want to
surface you know products that a user is
looking
for but there's inventory associated
with that product right we don't want to
surface products that have been sold out
or not available and so yes there's
definitely things that we can do and
think about in terms of extracting
entities from our query text and then
applying those as filters but then
there's a whole another space of filters
that can apply regardless of what that
text actually is and so I think in both
of these situations we can think about
you know how this applies but you
necessarily don't need to solve this
extraction problem to take advantage of
some of these filtering techniques and
some of these filters you may want to
apply on your
data okay thank you we actually have a
question online to go to first uh Sean
Springer asks uh read the pre-filtering
approach I don't get how step one works
how how do you impose a classic
relational database query against an
index for of vector data so let's go
back to the slide here just so we all
know what we're talking about so with
this pre-filtering approach right we
have two steps the first we want to pull
out all the candidates that are
available and then on the second we
actually want to scan cross all those
results and determine which of those are
the most
relevant so with this I can actually
think about this say completely two
separate systems if I want to so on one
end let's say I have a a SQL database
over here I query that
database for the documents or for the
pieces of information that meet my
criteria and usually when I'm using this
pre-filtering approach hopefully I'm
only returning a small subset of these
documents but in many ways this could be
you know the entire collection um for
all that matters and so now I've
extracted all these do docment from my
database and they're potentially
residing in memory they be residing
within another service and then within
that service within that you know
potentially separate application I'm
then doing an EXO search across those so
all these documents have an embedding
associated with them and then I'm
running this computation across those
embedding and so where that resides
could really be a multitude of different
places but in the case where you have a
small number of documents this is a
process you can just simply run in
memory and you wouldn't need more or
less a separate index to actually
perform that
computation thank you so coming back to
the room will you have a question
here thanks it's more of a clarification
on the first question that was asked um
I understood you to be saying that you
consider implementations of hnsw to be
examples of this kind of converged
infrastructure that you're talking about
where you're combining when you're doing
like in place filtering with a vector
search is that a correct understanding
of what you were yeah so I think there's
a ton of products tools that are already
trying to solve for this I don't think
it's anything novel thinking about
combining Vector search plus let's say
the metadata filtering I think there's
been amazing advancements made there but
what happens when we think about you
know other type of indexes that you may
want to use with your vector search I
think in one case which think is really
interesting is something like a
geospatial right we talked about the
example where we may only to look at
accounts that are within a certain
geographic area or region I don't know
if that's been solved for yet not saying
it has or it hasn't but I think that
introduces another realm or a different
problem what if I also want to compute
statistics on my documents perhaps let's
think about you know recent page of
views how you know how many people have
visited a document in a given amount of
time that's something that actually
rends really well it's like a cner store
and perhaps like an analytics type of
database and again a different type of
index and so I think there's actually
been a ton of advancement in research
and like metadata filtering plus Spector
search but a big thing I want us all to
you think about is that there's a ton of
different indexes a ton of different
search patterns different algorithms
that we may also want to use with our
Vector search and that's where I think
there's a lot more learning that we can
do and a lot of research that we can
really borrow
from great thank you so we have no more
questions online at the moment but have
somebody right over there I no now you
need the mic so we can hear it on the
recording so
I here we are I'll pass this and oh
actually I'll come past thank you sorry
excuse sorry you tell I'm British I
apologize for
everything how's it going I'm Joe um I
think you raised a good point about
merging different indexes Beyond
metadata filtering right like metadata
filtering is something that's you know
we all kind of think is a really
powerful thing but is pretty
straightforward you know you can think a
lot of different ways of applying it but
a lot of people here I think are coming
from a place where there's an
established keyword search system you
know that we built built up that's
powerful right and merging that with
your vector search index is kind of how
you get to the next level
there are a few ways that I think you
know research and people have
brainstormed around this right like you
can use your Keyword Index separately
and a vector index that are separate and
you merge them together in some sort of
way as a way of metadata filtering like
run my keyword search use that as a
filter to refine my Vector search or
someone might say create a singular sort
of index like I know people like elastic
search and and Besa have been pushing
like you can make one index where you
have both you're running like a
reciprocal rank Fusion across both your
bm25 and your vector similarities to
merge those and I was wondering if you
have any experience or Insight with
customers you've worked on on sort of is
there kind of like a decision about
which of those sort of may lead to
possibly better results or how people
have done it because I know that it's
very easy to say take your keyword
search run that use this as a filter to
drive your vector search but it's much
more difficult to build a coherent index
that can do all of this in one specific
ranking operation or one specific search
relevance function that you're creating
from this index so do you have any
insight that you've maybe gathered from
your customers about these different
kinds of more advanced approaches than
you know like just simply like saying
like I can identify this let's just
restrict this space to that there are
like new developments there yeah so from
the customers I've worked with a lot of
times are doing this in completely
separate systems still right so we may
have vro database over here we may have
different search solution over here
essentially running those queries those
searches in parallel at the I have a
conglomeration of results and perhaps
then I have you know kind of a ranking
model that is then kind of extracting
and giving me let's say the you know top
10 most relevant so that's the the
biggest Paradigm I see today and I think
there's been and continue to make a lot
of progress here as we think about you
know Tech search and Vector search
working together but and I think we can
you know I think that's again a problem
that a lot of people are researching and
there's a lot of potential ways we can
solve that and again having this kind of
singular holistic index that supports
supports all these different patterns
but then what happens again what if I
want to add in a different type of
indexing structure right in this case
and as we talked about metadata
filtering is that a separate index how
would that work with this now kind of
holistic or perfect index that's
blending text and Vector search again we
could go to like the geospatial example
we could also go to like range indexes
when it comes to you know relevance and
and timing and so I think the the future
that I see is we're still going to have
multiple
indexes right
and if it's very domain specific and if
we know we only want two patterns I can
very much see using a specific solution
but as let's say you expand different
use cases you may augment your
application you may want different types
of results or you know provide different
results in different areas you
automatically may get into this indexing
problem and so that's I think what I'm
really like pushing forward for us to
think about and start solving that in
some ways we may never actually have
this like sufficiently clever index and
we should spend more time thinking about
how to actually balance and search
across these different indexes and so
ultimately I see a much more of a
conglomerate solution across you know
different indexes that we have
today okay we we're going to just take a
question online and then I'm we're kind
of running out of time I'm afraid sorry
stos you'll get a chance I'm sure um so
uh let's
see uh Hanan Fang uh does the criteria
to classify a filter selective or
non-selective depend on the domain
I think like any application is going to
be domain specific in a lot of ways but
I wouldn't say any domain you know has
you know Pur selected filters or purely
non- selected filters now I'm sure there
are situations where that's the case but
I think what I've seen and again you you
know I think some of the examples we
click through is that usually see a
blend sometimes it's very selective
things you want to filter on but other
times there maybe things that are less
selective and I think one of the
challenges here let's say when you're
initially developing your prototype
putting together PCC MVP you may feel
like you fit in one of these categories
right typically i f very nonselective or
typically very selective but again the
moment you get that in the hands of
customers you start to see how they're
using it and what they're experiencing
you want to augment that you want to
change things you want to improve things
again you may encounter a need then to
adopt let's say a different type of
filtering a different approach which may
be slight to non selective and different
from that initial set that you had
scoped thank you okay I think we're
going to end it there please give be
huge Applause to John thank you everyone